Guide to the Carl Van Vechten Papers Relating to African American Arts and Letters
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs, 1932–1964; Series IV; 157.31 linear feet
  - Color Slides, 5.16 linear feet
    - Events
      - Wedding Reception for Carmen De Lavallade and Geoffrey Holder at the Clarence Derwent House, Westport, Connecticut
        - Camacho, Leu, with Elaine De Lavallade, Hubert Dilworth, and Lew Smith, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1899. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Camacho, Leu, with Elaine De Lavallade, Hubert Dilworth, Geoffrey Holder, and Lew Smith, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1900. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Carroll, Diahann, and Carl Van Vechten, 1955 June 26; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1897, 1898. No image set number. Photographs by Saul Mauriber.
        - Collins, Janet, and Carl Van Vechten, 1955 June 26; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1890, 1891. No image set number. Photographs by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, 1955 June 26; 4 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1875, 1876, 1877, 1878. No image set number. Photographs by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, and Lucille Lortel, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1880. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, with Elaine De Lavallade, Arthur Holder, and Louise de Frense Holder, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1885. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, with Elaine De Lavallade, Arthur Holder, Geoffrey Holder, and Louise de Frense Holder, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1886. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, with Geoffrey Holder, and Fania Marinoff, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1881. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, with Geoffrey Holder, and Lucille Lortel being photographed by Carl Van Vechten, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1879. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - De Lavallade, Carmen, with Geoffrey Holder, Fania Marinoff, and Carl Van Vechten, 1955 June 26; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1882, 1883. No image set number. Photographs by Saul Mauriber.
        - Decorations, Paper Lanterns, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1887. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Holder, Geoffrey, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1884. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Holder, Michael, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1889. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Johnson, Louis, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1893. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Premice, Josephine, 1955 June 26; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1895, 1896. No image set number. Photographs by Saul Mauriber.
        - Premice, Josephine, and Carl Van Vechten, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1894. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
        - Wedding cake, 1955 June 26; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 1888. No image set number. Photography by Saul Mauriber.
    - Places
      - Georgia. Atlanta
        - Atlanta University, 1957 May 15; 1 color slide (Box 223)
          Slide number 171a. Image set number CXIIc.
      - New York City. Manhattan
        This group of color slides documents walks by Van Vechten through and near the Harlem neighborhood on September 4 and October 5, 1940.
        Arranged by slide number.
        - Harlem. Salem United Methodist Church, 1940 September 4; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1, 2. Image set number CCXVII.
        - Harlem. Salem United Methodist Church, Rectory, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 3. Image set number CCXVII. Residence of Countee Cullen, 1918-1925.
        - Harlem. Tree of Hope (Wishing Tree), 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 4. Image set number CCXVII. Tree of Hope was an elm tree that originally stood in front of the Lafayette Theatre between 131st and 132nd Streets. On November 4, 1934, Bill Robinson replanted its stump on a traffic island on 7th Avenue at West 131st Street.
        - Harlem. James Weldon Johnson Residence, 1940 September 4; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 5, 6. Image set number CCXVII. Home of James Weldon Johnson from 1925 to 1938, at 187 West 135th Street. Van Vechten misidentifies the site as 187 West 134th Street.
        - Harlem. Saint Nicholas Historic District, 1940 September 4; 4 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 7, 8, 9, 10. Image set number CCXVII. Also known as "Striver's Row."
        - Harlem. Dunbar Apartments, 1940 September 4; 8 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Image set number CCXVIII. Includes views of buildings and portraits of children and a woman, likely at the on-site child care.
        - Harlem. Dunbar Apartments, 1940 September 4; 6 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. Image set number CCXVIII. Image numbers 19, 20, 22, 23, 24, 25, misidentified as Dunbar Apartments. Includes views of buildings and public sculpture including "Bears Playing" by Heinz Warneke, and "Motherhood" by Richmond Barthé.
        - Harlem. Fat Man on the Hill restaurant, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 25. Image set number CCXVIII. Front window of the restaurant, also known as Fat Man on Sugar Hill or Fat Man's Bar and Grill, owned by Charles "Fat Man" McKinley Turner and Edward Mallory at 450 West 155th Street.
        - Harlem. Harlem River and Polo Grounds, 1940 September 4; 4 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 26, 27, 28, 29. Image set number CCXVIII. Image numbers 26 and 28 depict a partial panorama, and image number 27 and 29 document the Polo Grounds.
        - Harlem. Paul Robeson Residence, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 30. Image set number CCXVIII. Home of Paul Robeson from 1939 to 1941 at 555 Edgecombe Avenue.
        - Washington Heights. Morris-Jumel Mansion, 1940 September 4; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 31, 32. Image set number CCXVIII.
        - Washington Heights. Sylvan Terrace, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 33. Image set number CCXVIII.
        - Harlem. Colonial Park, 1940 September 4; 15 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48. Image set number CCXIX. Views of the Colonial Park Pool and swimmers. In 1978, the park at West 146th Street and Broadhurst Avenue was renamed Jackie Robinson Park. The swimming pool by Robert Moses was completed in 1936.
        - Harlem. A'Lelia Walker Robinson Pied-à-terre, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 49. Image set number CCXIX. Pied-à-terre of A'Lelia Walker Robinson from circa 1919 to 1931 at 80 Edgecombe Avenue.
        - Morningside Heights. Morningside Park, 1940 September 4; 6 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55. Image set numbers. CCXIX and CCXX. Image numbers 50 and 51 also include portions of buildings at Columbia College, an undergraduate college at Columbia University.
        - Harlem. Street Scenes, 1940 September 4; 3 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 56, 57, 58. Image set number CCXX.
        - Harlem. Fred M. Williams Funeral Home, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 59. Image set number CCXX. Funeral home at 249 West 128th Street.
        - Harlem. Lafayette Theatre, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 60. Image set number CCXX. Entertainment venue located at 132nd Street and 7th Avenue.
        - Harlem. Elks Rendezvous Lounge, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 61. Image set number CCXX. Nightclub at 464 Lenox Avenue at 132nd Street.
        - Harlem. Lenox Avenue, 1940 September 4; 4 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 62, 63, 64, 66. Image set number CCXX. Image number 62 shows the R & L Bake Shops at 474 Lenox Avenue, and other images document street produce vendors.
        - Harlem. Harlem Hospital, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 65. Image set number CCXX. Hospital at 506 Lenox Avenue.
        - Harlem. Savoy Ballroom, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 67. Image set number CCXX. Ballroom at 596 Lenox Avenue.
        - Harlem. Fifth Avenue and West 134th Street, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 68. Image set number CCXX. View of street signs at the intersection.
        - Harlem. Street Portrait of a Girl, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 69. Image set number CCXX.
        - Harlem. Mount Morris Park, 1940 September 4; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 70, 71. Image set number CCXX. In 1973, the park bounded by 120th Street and 124th Street and by Madison Avenue was renamed Marcus Garvey Memorial Park.
        - Harlem. Jimmie Daniels Inc., 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 72. Image set number CCXL. Nightclub at 114 West 116th Street, misidentified by Van Vechten as 125th Street.
        - Harlem. Saint Mary Magdalene Catholic Church and Tru-Art Beauty Salon, 1940 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 73, 74. Image set number CCXL. Beauty salon on the first floor and American Catholic Church (Syro-Antiochian) on the second floor at 189 Lenox Avenue.
        - Harlem. Lenox Avenue, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 75. Image set number CCXL. View of a three-story brick house that Van Vechten identifies as owned by a white family.
        - Harlem. Bronze Studio, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 76, 77. Image set number CCXL. Dance studio at 227 Lenox Avenue, which included a Tillie's Resturant in the garden floor. Views includes partial views of a campaign billboard for presidential candidate Wendell Willkie.
        - Harlem. Lenox Avenue, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 78. Image set number CCXL. View of row houses.
        - Harlem. Hotel Theresa, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 79. Image set number CCXL. Hotel at 2082-2096 Seventh Avenue between West 124th and 125th Streets.
        - Harlem. Love and Friendship Spiritualist Church, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 80. Image set number CCXL. Spiritualist church at 423 Lenox Avenue.
        - Harlem. First Emmanuel Church, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 81. Image set number CCXL. Church at 105 West 130th Street.
        - Harlem. Doorway, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 82. Image set number CCXL.
        - Harlem. Saint James Evangelical Orthodox Church and Solomon's Glass, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 83. Image set number CCXL. Church and business at 451 Lenox Avenue.
        - Harlem. Odds & Ends Sewing Shop and Blue Globe Restaurant, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 84. Image set number CCXLI. Businesses at 453 Lenox Avenue.
        - Harlem. Lenox Avenue, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 85. Image set number CCXLI.
        - Harlem. Peace Mission Restaurant at West 134th Street, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 86. Image set number CCXLI.
        - Harlem. Dickie Wells, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 87. Image set number CCXLI. Nightclub at 169 West 133rd Street from 1932 to 1942.
        - Harlem. Street Portrait of Children, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 88. Image set number CCXLI.
        - Harlem. New York Public Library, 135th Street Branch, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 89. Image set number CCXLI. Branch library at 103 West 135th Street, renamed the Countee Cullen Branch in 1951. Inscription misidentifies the location as a police station.
        - Harlem. Young Men's Christian Association of the City of New York., 135th Street Branch, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 90. Image set number CCXLI. Located at 180 West 135the Street; location misidentified by Van Vechten as West 134th Street.
        - Harlem. Smalls Paradise, 1940 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 91, 92. Image set number CCXLI. Nightclub at 2294 Seventh Avenue.
        - Harlem. The Big Apple, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 93. Image set number CCXLI. Restaurant at 2300 Seventh Avenue at the intersection with West 134th Street.
        - Harlem. Lincoln Theatre, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 94. Image set number CCXLI. Theater at 56-58 West 135th Street; location misidentified by Van Vechten as West 134th Street.
        - Harlem. Lincoln Theatre, Thomas Ward with a poster for his play, "Big White Fog", 1940 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 95, 96. Image set number CCXLI.
        - Harlem. Powell Lindsay, probably near the Lincoln Theatre, 1940 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 97, 98. Image set number CCXLI.
        - Harlem. Young Women's Christian Association, Emma Ransom House, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 99. Image set number CCXLI. Residence for women at 175 West 137th Street.
        - Harlem. The 111 Club, 1940 October 5; 1 color slide (Box 225)
          Slide number 100. Image set number CCXLI. Nightclub at 111 West 136th Street.
        - Harlem. Apollo Theater, 1940 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 101, 102. Image set number CCXLI. Music hall at 253 West 125th Street
        - Harlem. Peace Mission Movement extension, 1940 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 103, 104. Image set number CCXLI. An extension of the movement established by Father Devine at 36-38 West 123rd Street at the intersection with Lenox Avenue.
      - Pennsylvania
        - Erie. Historical marker for birthplace of H. T. (Harry Thacker) Burleigh, 1952 June 11; 1 color slide (Box 223)
          Slide number 309. No image set number.
        - Philadelphia. North 25th Street and Ridge Avenue. James Weldon Johnson Homes, 1941 September 27; 12 color slides (Box 225)
          Slide numbers 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Image set number CCCLXXV. Views of the federal housing project. Includes informal portraits of children.
      - Tennessee. Nashville. Fisk University
        - Carl Van Vechten Gallery of Fine Arts, 1957 May 14; 1 color slide (Box 224)
          Slide number 882C. No image set number.
        - Library, 1957 May 14; 1 color slide (Box 224)
          Slide number 882A. No image set number. Also known as Erastus Milo Cravath Memorial Library.
        - Library, 1949 November 4; 1 color slide (Box 224)
          Slide number 882B. No image set number. Also known as Erastus Milo Cravath Memorial Library.
    - Artwork
      Arranged alphabetically by surname of the artist followed by works by unidentified creators.
      - Barthé, Richmond. Julius, circa 1940, sculpture with a feathered headdress, 1940 November 20; 3 color slides (Box 223)
        Slide numbers 26, 27, 28. Image set number CCLXXVII.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Carmen, circa 1954, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-8. Image set number CLc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Eartha Kit t, circa 1954, painting, 1954 October 5; 2 color slides (Box 226)
        Slide numbers 1079, 1191-1. Image set number LVIIIc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Henry, circa 1958, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-7. Image set number CLc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Model (also known as Portrait of a Negro NY), circa 1958, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-3. Image set number CLc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Nude, circa 1958, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-6. Image set number CLc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Orphan, circa 1958, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-2. Image set number CLc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Portrait of Larry, circa 1958, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-5. Image set number CLc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Self-Portrait, circa 1954, painting, 1954 September 21; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1185. Image set number XLIIc.
      - Cleveland, Lady Bird. Voodoo Dance, circa 1958, painting, 1958 July 28; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1191-4. Image set number CLc.
      - Cortor, Eldzier. Quartet No. VI, 1948, painting, 1959 June 7; 1 color slide (Box 226)
        Slide number 2078. Image set number CXLVIIIc. Inscription on mount misidentifies the date as June 9, 1959.
      - Cortor, Eldzier. Trio V, circa 1948, painting, 1959 June 7; 1 color slide (Box 226)
        Slide number 2077. Image set number CXLVIIIc. Inscription on mount misidentifies the date as June 9, 1959.
      - Holder, Geoffrey. Voodoo Ceremony (Self-portrait), 1955, painting, 1955 June 17; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 1539. Image set number LXXXVc.
      - Simpson, Merton D. (Merton Daniel). Night Village, circa 1955-1959, painting, 1959 July 21; 1 color slide (Box 226)
        Slide number 2080. Image set number CLXIXc.
      - Wilson, Ellis, Marchand, circa 1947, painting, 1959 August 12; 1 color slide (Box 224)
        Slide number 969 (1). Image set number CLIc.
      - Poster for the Ed Sullivan Show in Moscow, Soviet Union, 1959 September 29; 2 color slides (Box 224)
        Slide numbers 1600, 1603. Image set number CLIIIc.
      - Unidentified artist from Africa. Mask, undated, used as frontpiece for Black Ritual (Obeah), ballet choreographed by Agnes de Mille, music by Darius Milhaud, 1953 August 12; 1 color slide (Box 223)
        Slide number 453. Image set number XXXVIc. Manuscript inscription identifies the work as Dark Ritual.